Chapter 3. Cat, caught, cut. A equals ah, O equals ah, U equals uh. After laying our
foundation with intonation and liaisons, here we finally begin to refine your
pronunciation. We're now going to work on the differences between ah, ah, and uh, as
well as O, A, and eh. Let's start out with the ah sound. The ah sound. Although not a
common sound, A is very distinctive to the ear and is typically American. In the
practice paragraph, this sound occurs five times. As its phonetic symbol indicates, A
is a combination of A and E. To pronounce it, drop your jaw down as if you're going
to say A, but then from that position, try to say E. The final sound is not two
separate vowels, but rather the end result of the combination. It's very close to the
sound that a goat makes. MAAH! Try it a few times now. AW, AA, AW, AA. If you find
yourself getting too nasal with AA, pinch your nose as you say it. If cat turns into
can't, you need to pull the sound out of your nose and down into your throat. Note,
as you look for the AA sound, you might think that words like down or sound have
an AA in them. For this diphthong, try A plus O, or OU. This way, down would be
written da-own. Because it's a combined sound, however, it's not included in the
cat category. The AH sound. The AH sound occurs a little more frequently. You'll
find ten such sounds in the exercise. To pronounce AH, relax your tongue and drop
your jaw as far down as it'll go. As a matter of fact, put your hand under your
chin and say ma-pa-ta-sa. Your hand should be pushed down by your jaw as it opens.
Remember, it's the sound you make when the doctor wants to see your throat, so open
it up and drop your jaw. The schwa sound. Last is the schwa, the most common sound
in American English. When you work on a practice paragraph, depending on how fast
you speak, how smoothly you make liaisons, how strong your intonation is, and how
much you relax your sounds, you'll find from 50 to 75 schwas. Spelling doesn't
help identify it because it can appear as any one of the vowels or a combination of
them. It's a neutral vowel sound, uh. It's usually in an unstressed syllable, though
it can be stressed as well. Whenever you find a vowel that can be crossed out and
its absence wouldn't change the pronunciation of the word, you've probably
found a schwa. Photography. The two apostrophes show the location of the
neutral vowel sounds. Because it's so common, however, the wrong pronunciation
of this one little sound can leave your speech strongly accented, even if you
Americanized everything else. Note, some dictionaries use two different written
symbols, the upside-down E and the upside-down V, We're only going to use the first
one silent or neutral a schwa is neutral, but it's not silent By comparison the
silent e at the end of a word is a signal for pronunciation, but it's not pronounced
itself Code is code the e tells you to say an o if you leave the e off you have cod
The schwa on the other hand is neutral, but it's an actual sound uh For example
you could also write photography as fa ta gra fee Because it's a neutral sound, the
schwa doesn't have any distinctive characteristics, yet it is the most common
sound in the English language. To make the uh sound, put your hand on your diaphragm
and push until a grunt escapes. Don't move your jaw, tongue, or lips. Just allow the
sound to flow past your vocal cords. It should sound like uh. Once you master this
sound, you will have an even easier time with pronouncing can and can't. In a
sentence, can't sounds like can't, But, can becomes kun unless it is stressed when
it is can. I can do it. I can't do it. Vowel chart. In the vowel chart that
follows, the four corners represent the four most extreme positions of the mouth.
The center box represents the least extreme position, the neutral schwa. For
these four positions, only move your lips and jaw. Your tongue should stay in the
same place, with the tip resting behind the bottom teeth. One to pronounce beat
your lips should be drawn back, but your teeth should be close together Your mouth
should form the shape of a banana Two to pronounce boot your lips should be fully
rounded and your teeth should be close together Your mouth should form the shape
of a Cheerio Three to pronounce bought drop your jaw straight down from the boot
position your mouth should form the shape of an egg Four, to pronounce bat, keep
your jaw down, pull your lips back, and try to simultaneously say ah and eh. Your
mouth should form the shape of a box. Note, word-by-word pronunciation will be
different than individual sounds within a sentence. That, than, as, at, and, have,
had, can, and so on contain eh sounds when they stand alone, but they are weak words
that reduce quickly in speech.